And so, if you look at Koch, like macro,
um high level, one of the largest
private companies
um in the country. Today, we touch the
majority of the economy, as I mentioned,
and operate in about 60 countries.
Um 145,000
employees um and growing. I would say
the biggest differentiator of Koch and
why we've been able to grow
now over 10,000x
since the early '60s is because of
>> Ladies and gentlemen, we have a very
special treat today. I'm going to sit
down with Chase Koch. He's a member of
the Koch family, which owns Koch
Industries. They're one of the largest
private companies in America. Chase
recently wrote a book with his father,
Charles. It's called Becoming a
Principle-Driven Leader, 41 Principles
to Build an Enduring Business. In this
conversation, Chase and I go through
what is it like to build Koch
Industries? How do they apply these 41
principles? What exactly can you use
these principles to transform your life,
your business, and broader society? This
conversation is fascinating because it
takes us behind the scenes. We
understand not only the business deals
that they've done, the failures that
they've had, but also how they apply
these principles in their business, in
their investments, and into technology.
And I think that you're going to take
away a lot from this conversation. It's
one of my favorite conversations I've
had on the podcast in a very long time.
Chase is an incredible person and it's
very fun hanging out with him. And so,
here's my conversation with Chase Koch.
All right, Chase. I thought a great
place to start is Koch Disruptive
Technologies. I think it's kind of been
your baby inside of the organization.
And really, it to me is a microcosm of
so much of the principles that has made
this business amazing. What was the
original idea for creating this
Disruptive Technology Group?
>> Well, the original idea, we hadn't
really we had dabbled in venture capital
back in the early 2000s, but we went
away from it. But, this was 2016-2017,
and it started with, like, where my
passion was, really. Um and I've always
been kind of cut out of this cloth of
innovation and this principle that we
actually talk about in our book called
creative destruction. Which is Joseph
Schumpeter's principle of you've got to
disrupt yourself from within, otherwise
the market will do it to you and you'll
become a dinosaur.
And I've since I was a little kid, I
always wanted to be working on the next
thing, the next curve. Not like what was
right
in front of me. And I've been working in
the operating businesses since I was 15
years old. And so again, back 2016-17,
this is when technology really started
taking off and reshaping
industries and I was in our ag business
at the time in our fertilizer business.
And I saw an opportunity to well, first
of all, I saw what technology was doing
to our value chain. And there were two
companies and two founders that really
kind of rocked me back and I was like
something is happening to ag and we need
to be paying attention. We we need to
understand the creative destruction
that's happening in our industry. One
was Climate Corp, which was David
Friedberg
who ended up, you know, really looking
at data science for the first time in
agriculture and looking at weather data,
looking at soil data and he built a
company around that and sold data
analytics to farmers.
And I remember having a relationship
with him because we were we were working
on actually swapping data. I was working
on enhanced efficiency fertilizers and
the uptake of nitrogen
for farmers and how to optimize that so
they could do more with less. And he was
all the data science behind it. So we
started working on doing data exchanges
to help each other. And then he calls me
one day and says, "Actually Monsanto
just bought the company." I was like,
"You're just getting started. You got
like 10 to 20 million in revenue, you
know? And he said, "Yeah, but they paid
me $1.1 billion for it." And that was
like the first shot across the bow, I
think, in technology and agriculture,
and that just woke me up.
>> Because you were like, that's crazy they
paid so much money for a company that
>> it was that, but also just the wake up
of the the value that was being created
with data science.
And we hadn't really been focused on
that. And so, that one and then another
friend of mine, Amol Deshpande, that
created a Farmers Business Network,
which was basically the model of the
Amazon of agriculture, and being able to
go
direct to farmer, and some of the some
of the the services that he was
providing, I thought was really, really
interesting. And he could only do that
because of the technology where the
technology was going to enable that
business model.
So, I just basically went to the team
and went to Koch leadership and said,
"We have to be a part of these
companies." We had because that is going
to enable us to see what is going to
disrupt our core business with our our
nitrogen production assets and our
global trading business.
Um
but I'll also just be a part of that
next curve, whatever it's going to be.
And so, that was the birth of Koch
Disruptive Technologies. We started
looking at it from just an ag
perspective, but we talked as a
leadership team, we said, "If we're
going to really invest in companies like
Climate Corp and Farmers Business
Network, we should be doing that across
all of Koch." So, what are the companies
that are going to disrupt Koch
long-term, and we need to see those
early, and we need to actually have skin
in the game and invest on invest in them
in a meaningful way.
And so, that was the birth of of Koch
Disruptive Technologies. But, I would
say back to the principles at play and
why
why I wanted to do that.
One, I talked about creative destruction
and how important that is for the future
of Koch, but two, the mutual benefit.
And that I felt that we could offer
Koch as a laboratory because we Koch
touches the majority of the economy.
We're like 80% of the various industries
where because we're very very broad. And
so when you look at that from a
technology founder's perspective, so
that you know many imagine a software
company they want to sell to all these
industries, right? So to to be able to
have one phone call into Koch and be
able to sell 10 different operating
companies across the economy, that's
pretty valuable to a you know a new
startup.
And so we can help them as a customer
like that, as a supplier, as a subject
matter expert. We have 140,000
employees, we're in 60 countries. So I
was like that is a laboratory for a
founder. And so the benefit that we can
we can bring them by being that
capability provider, not just money
and capital, but by by really bringing
capability to them in a differentiated
way. That was the benefit to them, but
the benefit to us the mutual benefit
side of that was we're going to see
around corners and what in ways that
other companies can't.
>> What is Koch Industries? I think that's
like a question you know I asked a
couple of friends before we did this and
I said what do you want to know? And
that was probably the number one
question was just like I know it's
successful. I know it's you know the
first or second largest private company
in America. I know they do 125 plus
billion dollars of revenue and this is
like amazing thing.
How? What what is it? Maybe let's start
there.
>> Yeah, well I mean I think because we're
private that is that's probably the
number one question because we don't we
we don't report publicly. And I think
also there's a learning there. You roll
back the clock 15-20 years ago, we
didn't do a good job of getting our
story out. And so that's one of the
reasons why I'm excited to hear to be
here talking with you. It's like I I
want to get the story out. Who is Koch?
What What do we do? Why do we do it?
What are our principles?
Um and so if you look at Koch like
macro, um high level, probably one of
the largest private companies
um in the country.
Um my grandfather started the company um
back the predecessor company to Koch
back in the '40s. My father took over in
in 1961. Today we touch the majority of
the economy as I mentioned and operate
in about 60 countries.
Um 145,000
employees um and growing.
And um
I would say the biggest differentiator
of Koch and why we've been able to grow
now over 10,000 X since the early '60s
is because of our principle-based
management framework um that my father
basically
kind of founded and with the help of
many many um leaders at Koch really
comes down to the empowering people from
the bottom up with principles. Not
top-down telling people what to do and
the only way you can scale a company in
our in our view and our in our
experience is when you have a
principle-based framework that you can
empower people with, help them
understand the principles, and let them
run.
>> It's interesting the way that we
originally got connected was uh I read
your father's uh one of his books uh
Good Profit and I wrote this uh kind of
notes that I took on it and um in the
book uh he when he defines what Good
Profit is, this idea of actually being
able to derive it based on these
principles versus you know kind of
political advantage or regulatory
capture. Yeah. But the second piece that
I think uh if I had to take one thing
away from it and I've just almost like
you know you you find like a a kindred
soul, right? Or you find like somebody
who has this idea and you're like, "Oh
my god, I can't believe somebody else
you know thinks this way."
>> Yeah.
>> Is he had gone back and he had studied
all the great civilizations and
basically said, "What made these
civilizations or these economies work?"
>> He did.
>> And in the book he outlines, here's you
know, a couple of core principles that
he had identified. And then he's like,
"Well, how do we take these and put them
inside of a company?" And I don't think
a lot of people think of a business the
same way they think of an economy or a
civilization.
Um but when I was reading about maybe
your personal experience
>> Yeah.
>> sounds like he in that process also
would sit you down every Sunday
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
>> give you, you know,
a version of Sunday school but kind of
the economic version.
>> exactly right. Yeah, you want me to get
into that?
>> I would love to hear what was going on
in these conversations.
>> Yeah, it's it's fascinating and it's
been such a journey for me as Charles
Koch's son and I would say my sister
would say the same.
Um but you know, to your point, he
studied he's so intellectually curious.
He always wanted to know how does the
world work and what drives human
progress? And he studied everyone. This
this is start of his, you know, mid to
late 20s he got the bug and he just went
down the the rabbit hole and read all
the philosophers, Hayek, Von Mises,
um Milton Friedman, you know, economics,
philosophy, history. But he also he
studied, this is what I think a lot of
people probably miss, he applied the
scientific method to his own learning
which means you try to disprove your
hypothesis as much as you try to prove
it. Um so I mean, he he he studied Mao,
he studied Lenin,
um
uh Hitler and like what what how did why
did they make the decisions that they
did? But then you're right, from there
understand these principles, good
principles and bad principles, the ones
that drove human progress and the ones
that that um
that made us go into into decline and
then said, "Okay, um,
now let's look at different countries.
Why did Venezuela not succeed? And why
did Chile as a comparison? Hong Kong
versus China. North Korea, South Korea."
And just studied that, um, and then
pulled out the principles that drove the
most human progress, your point, and
then brought those into does this work
inside a company? The same principles of
what has driven human progress, can they
work inside a firm? And that was early
'80s were the first experiments on what
is now principle-based management. But
as a kid, back to your point, um, I
don't know, I must have been 10, 11
years old. My sister's 2 years older
than me.
Um, he wanted us to learn the same
things that he was learning, that he was
passionate about, so we'd have, um,
Sunday philosophy, economics lessons.
And you can imagine, like, my sister is
a much better student, um, than I was.
She's still way smarter than I am, but
um, you know, she would be like kind of
front of the classroom taking it all in
and just
Well, because he would he would quiz us
every 15 minutes. Okay, what did I just
talk about? There was always
accountability, always.
And I'd be there, you know, with my hat
kind of pulled over my eyes, half
asleep, you know, and I I'd be the
failing
Yeah, the failing student um, in the in
the philosophy course. Um, but what I
would tell you, going from that as a
kid, um, to when the light bulb actually
went off, it was probably my late 20s.
And it was I was running one of the uh,
business units of the fertilizer
business. I spent about a decade in our,
um, Coke fertilizer. And I was running
our international business and we were
building a fertilizer terminal in
Brazil.
And Brazil's one of the biggest import
markets.
Agriculture is their their biggest
industry.
And I went in with a few other leaders
very naively into Brazil thinking, "Oh,
we're going to build this high-speed
terminal. It's going to be great.
Farmers are going to get their product
faster. We're going to run a more
efficient system at the port." It was in
Paranaguá, Brazil. And I we spent a year
working on this.
And we got the deal done with a local
partner.
Very excited.
We thought we'd have the terminal built
within 9 months. Ended up taking us 4
years.
And so, you know, bureaucracy, red tape,
protectionism,
all the principles that my father like
was telling me about when I was 10, 11,
12 years old. You don't get it until you
actually live it.
>> Experience it all.
>> I experienced it myself. I felt it. I
felt the pain of that. I felt the pain
for those that worked, you know, in that
value chain, the farmer, the terminal
operators. And there like there's
there's not progress. There's not
innovation. There's not creative
destruction if you put all these
barriers around a business. It can't
advance. It won't get better. And so, I
lived that.
And that's when I was like light bulbs
going off.
Mutual benefit.
Openness. Creative destruction.
You know, a number of other principles
at play there. But then I was like,
"Okay, I'm going to start to really pay
attention. I'm going to start to study
this. I'm going to see how that applies
to my job and my life."
The other thing that was really
interesting, I think, about, you know,
my sister and I growing up in the family
of Charles and Liz Koch was
the focus on values and principles at
the dinner table. So, yeah, there's the
economics and the philosophy part of it.
But just the accountability
when he and amazingly he'd be home from
work at 6:00 p.m. every He's building
this amazing company, but his focus on
developing us as kids was I look back on
it now with you know, three kids myself.
I'm like, how did you do that?
Um but he did it and he did it by
consistent consistency
and accountability of values and
principles. We'd come home at 6:00 he'd
sit down and say, "Okay, what are the
five things?" As love, courage, faith,
honor, and loyalty. That was our you
know, we were little kids, right?
And um
>> And those [clears throat] were five like
almost family
>> are
yeah, our value system that we started
with. Now it would evolve over time into
economic principles and that sort of
thing. You know,
>> A lot of a lot of fun. [laughter]
>> A lot of fun. Let me tell you about good
profit versus bad profit. But but the my
point being is that um we'd sit down and
Elizabeth and I would both have to
articulate a story from that day on how
we exemplified one of those principles.
So I I share that because it's these
principles they're not just business
principles to to you know, build a great
business.
Um you can apply them to anything and
everything. Non- You're building a
non-profit. You're you're running a
sports team. You're raising your kids.
The these principles apply to everything
and what was amazing about my father was
his consistency
to apply it to every I'd say consistency
but also courage.
>> Mhm.
>> Um because you know, I mean when he
applied them more broadly outside of
business, he caught a lot of hell for
it. You know, um
there's a lot of folks in the media that
um pounded him for what he believed, but
if you have courage and conviction over
something that and you studied something
about you know, what drives the most
human progress over time and I want to
help the most people that I can,
you'll take the arrows for it. And and
and that's what he did. And I I think
this goes to why we we wrote this book.
Um
I think what the the the 41 principles
and becoming a principle-driven leader
that that we have in there,
that's um is really a navigation tool
for someone that's building a business
or like I said, hopefully help them in
every aspect of their life. Cuz we are
living in a time of unprecedented
uncertainty, whether it's economic
uncertainty, whether it's, you know, are
we going to lose our jobs to AI, or a
you know, a lot of divisiveness in our
culture.
Um we believe that a a clear principles
framework doesn't have to be our 41.
These are just the ones that have helped
us the most. But if you don't have a
clear framework or
or tool set, how are you going to
navigate all this uncertainty? If you
don't, you're just going to blow with
the wind, and like whatever what you
know, especially the next generation,
what what's trending, what's cool, what
people are liking on social media. So,
we feel like we got lucky with the
timing of putting this out. Like we are
in a time of unprecedented uncertainty.
How do we get these principles out to as
many people as we can to help them with
that framework?
>> You know, what's interesting is um
"Tolerance is the virtue of those who
don't stand for anything." is a a famous
quote. And you know, you mentioned I
think that your father, but really the
business, and I think you know, it's
very obvious talking with you,
um
you almost start with like, what do you
believe as an individual? And then what
do you believe that a company stands
for, which is just a collection of
individuals? And then what does society
stand for? And a lot of that
divisiveness, etc., I think is um
there's a clash of ideas right at the
societal level which frankly I don't
think that there is like a
one-size-fits-all solution. People
always disagree. They've disagreed for
centuries. They will disagree well after
we are all gone.
>> Right.
>> But at an individual level I'm always
surprised that you know even if you're
just interviewing a candidate for a job
and you're like you know
what what do you want to do with your
life? Like the intentionality is you
know sometimes not there or you know
what type of company do you want to work
at? And they're kind of like you know
one that pays me well.
>> Yeah totally. Whereas I feel like you
guys almost are so clear in what you
individually believe and what a company
believes that it does probably serve as
a huge magnet for talent. You got
145,000 people that work for you.
>> Yes.
>> But I wouldn't be surprised if it
actually repels away some people too.
>> But my guess is that you guys aren't
upset about that. Like it's kind of like
hey we want the right people to come
here and work here right?
>> Yeah no I mean so one of our the
principles that we have that we we
really frame up and spend a lot of time
on in the book is talent.
And I would say you know one
principle-based management is our our
biggest competitive advantage that we
have in the market. Um it's our
operating system. I mean it's how we do
business. And and one really critical
element of that is our talent vision and
how we apply the principle of talent.
And that is
um
we hire on values first
skill second and credentials last.
I would say that's one of our biggest
differentiators as a company.
>> What does that What does that mean like
>> Well so so I'll give you some examples.
So most companies I think are the
opposite. Credentials first.
>> Where'd you go to school? What companies
you work at before?
>> your GPA and all that?
And we feel like all that's nonsense.
I mean yes you have to have a gift. You
have to have an intelligence that the
company needs you know and fill a gap
that we have but we look at it at it as
we want someone that is contribution
motivated. This is another principle in
the book. Very very important. Someone's
contribution motivated, they want to
come in, they don't think they know
everything, they're humble, they're open
to a challenge process,
and that they it's all I call it like we
want the farm team kids. The kids that
they didn't have to work on a farm, but
they come with that grit and that value
system of work ethic, and that they
they've got to earn their position. They
have to earn the money that they're
that
you know, their base salary and their
bonus. Just because they came from an
Ivy League school and they have a 4.0
doesn't entitle them to anything, right?
And so that has served us very very
well, and honestly that's the one of the
reasons why we like being in Wichita,
Kansas, in the Midwest. Um and cuz we we
feel like we have access to a lot of
that talent, and some of these
overlooked um universities maybe that
some of the other big companies don't
focus on. They're like we want the cream
of the crop, the um the kids that have
the work ethic that are contribution
motivated, and um and bring them in. And
and I again, I would say that is
probably the biggest differentiator that
we have. I mean, it's all about your
team, you know,
we all know that. Um and
it's who you hire, but also who you
fire.
>> Mhm.
>> Um and you know, when you have people
that come in that are the opposite of
contribution motivated, and you're
wrong. I mean, in in a company our we're
wrong a lot. Hopefully our numbers are
getting better in terms of how many
times we miss this, but if you hire
someone that's more destructively
motivated or deficiency motivated and
comes in with that entitlement mindset
or victim mentality,
or even worse yet destructively
motivated where it's all about power and
control.
Um if my father were here, he would say
the biggest failures that we've had um
across the company is where we let a
destructively motivated leader, really
smart individual, end up being at the
top of the company and we leave them
there too long.
>> Mhm.
>> Because what that does to the culture of
the entire cuz everyone looks at the
leader.
>> They need to wait.
>> Right? Everyone looks at the leader and
a reflection of the leader's behaviors
and
and um the expectations of the leader
and how he or she holds themselves. So
everything downstream of a destructively
motivated leader is going to be a
problem. Right? It takes years to clean
that up.
So uh it was interesting. We had our
board meeting last week and I was
looking around the room. We have 12
different business units.
And um
five of the 12 were basically I call
them kids, but kids that I grew up with
when I came back from what I graduated
from Texas A&M and then came back in and
was finding my way around Coke. These
were um
you know, uh young guys that I worked
with. They were right out of school, 21
to 24 years old and they're now running
five of the 12 businesses at Coke. So
that speaks just to our our talent
model.
>> Mhm.
>> It's like
it um not only
values first, skills second, credentials
last, but then once they're in, if they
make a contribution, there's no
corporate ladder.
>> Mhm.
>> They can go from this business to that
business, running supply chain to being
CEO of a company.
>> Mhm.
>> Um I'll give you one example. Um the
gentleman that I worked with in business
development when we bought
Georgia-Pacific back in 2005, largest
acquisition we at Coke has ever done,
still to this day.
Um I think he was 20 years old, 21, and
he was the lead finance and an analysis
on that entire acquisition
at at 21. And now he's the CEO of
Guardian Glass, which is a global glass
manufacturer. I'm just like looking
around the room going, this is a it's
amazing. It's an incredible story. And
like looking at the boardroom was a
reflection of our talent model.
>> Today's episode is brought to you by
Figure Markets. All right, everyone, who
wants a slice of $160,000?
Our partner Figure's running a promo
where they're giving back to their
community. From July 27th to August
27th, any user who has never completed a
crypto-backed loan with them can qualify
for this giveaway. Check out the link in
my bio for more information. We're
living in a world of higher-for-longer
rates, tighter credit, [music] and fewer
places to earn real yield. That's why
Figure is interesting. Figure's the
largest non-bank HELOC lender in the
United States with over $22 billion
unlocked for homeowners. They're now
applying that same concept and
innovation to crypto-backed loans and
real-world asset yield. If you're
holding crypto, Figure lets you borrow
against it at 8.91% interest, which is
9.999%
APR with a [music] 50% loan-to-value,
giving you liquidity without selling,
without triggering taxes, and without
stepping out of the market. They use a
decentralized MPC custody, so assets
stay in segregated wallets, protected
from rug pulls, and they've introduced
liquidation protection to help manage
downside volatility.
>> [music]
>> And for investors looking for yield,
Democratized Prime offers up to 9% APY
paid hourly, backed by real-world
private credit, real cash flows, and not
speculative token emissions. Figure is
building a new capital market on
blockchain, and now you have access to
the upside. Check them out using the
link below.
>> When you're going through the like
interview process, right? It it's um
I think the way you get at like, what
are your values is very unique. Cuz what
you guys aren't screening for from at
least my my understanding is like,
you're not really like, "Hey, who's
woke? Who's not?" Like, that's kind of
like high-level, very simple stuff. But
it's actually this like contribution
mindset, right? It's understanding
almost of like, "Hey, do you understand
what a comparative advantage is and how
you implement it?" And and you know, the
ability to do some of this. What are you
doing in the interview to kind of suss
this out?
>> Um
We're [clears throat] learning all the
time, yeah.
>> Yeah, and and I'm asking from the
perspective of people who are watching
this are, you know, people who run tech
companies. They may be small business
owners. Some of them may even be big
business owners. And like, I think
that's one of the big questions that
people always have. It's like, "How do I
get better at analyzing the person
sitting across from me as to whether
they will be a good fit for my company
or not?"
>> Well, and the the downside of getting
that wrong is huge. Right? Just like we
talked about, the wrong destructively
motivated leader. Or if you miss on a
hire, it basically costs you 2 years.
>> Mhm.
>> Because you're going to wait 9 to 12
months to actually make a decision, give
that person a chance, then it doesn't
work out, go back into the market to try
to refill that, you know, that role.
That's that's another 6 months probably.
And then there's another 12 months of
development of that. And so, the real
cost of a bad hire is significant. So,
to your point, having a great capability
on how you do that up front is is is a
huge competitive advantage if you can
figure it out. So, the way the way we do
that is
um I mean, each business has their own,
you know, kind of HR capability. And the
business leaders are responsible for
their own process and how they do that.
So, this is not a cookie-cutter
approach. Um but what we try to apply is
um a an interview-based model. Um well,
I let me start with the the pipeline of
talent as well. Back to where you What
pond are you fishing in matters. Right?
And if you have a values-first mindset,
you want to be fishing in the right pond
that fits your business. So, we do that.
Um but then the second thing is the
interview process itself is we try to
get a lot of different people that are
skilled at different principles. So,
whether it's respect, humility,
challenge process,
um innovation and creative destruction.
Um you may be very good at the you know,
asking questions around innovation and
how thoughtful they are. Give me
examples when you've you know,
transformed a product or a system, a
process, improved a plant, whatever. Um
but I may be better at sussing out um
whether it's humility or integrity or
respect and some of these very squishy
kind of subjective um principles. So,
what we try to do is get a team of seven
or eight people to all hit, you know,
basically hit the interview process from
different angles.
And then we have like a 360 review
process where you know, everyone raise
their hand, would you um would you hire
this person or not and why? And give
give me the examples that you went
through on why you're confident this
individual is strong on the values side.
It's a lot more about the values than
the actual skills.
>> Interesting.
>> Um because we believe once you get them
in, if their contribution motivated and
they have the right raw material to
learn, that they can come in and learn
and we can teach them.
Um we take a little and this is also
like you have to take it's long-term
thinking versus short-term thinking even
on the talent development side.
So, um that's what I would say is it and
now what we're doing is applying AI to
this. And so, we're working with a
company called Happy Robot
>> Okay.
>> that is
>> What a name.
>> Yeah, yeah, exactly, [laughter]
exactly. I can't explain why it's called
that.
Um but it's it's pretty interesting. I
just got a um kind of a a a a
on this and some examples of how we're
leveraging it cuz even when you're doing
it at scale, I mean think about what I
just described. That takes a lot of
human capital and time and it's the most
important decision you make who you're
going to bring into the company, but if
you can complement that with artificial
intelligence and automate some of these
things to where the top of the filter,
you're getting to who are the
contribution motivated people these
candidates and these are the top 10 of
the 100 that we've talked to, you can
make it a lot more efficient and
hopefully improve your your batting
averages as well.
>> Yeah, when I was at Facebook, the
product manager interview track is very
similar. They have three people who
interview. One is more of a technical
interview, one's more kind of an
analytics interview and then one is just
pure company culture interview. They do
not tell the candidate, you know,
who's doing what and then afterwards, I
forget the exact details, but I think it
was all three have to go into the room
and has to be
at least two strong hires and no one can
be a you know, weak to to strong no
hire.
>> Yeah.
>> And
when you're like going through the
interview process, you're kind of just
like, hey, I'm talking to these people,
you know, I'm meeting whatever.
Then we're on the other side.
>> Yeah.
>> Like, oh, this is way more analytical.
This is way more intense than I thought.
You know, how the hell did I get in
here?
>> Yeah, it's almost like when you're doing
the interview, ignorance is bliss.
>> Yeah, you don't want to know. 100% 100%,
but you know, one of the things that I I
think is really interesting is you
mentioned AI and you know, we started
the conversation with these disruptive
technologies, but I think when most
people think of Coke Industries, they
think of the very hardcore agricultural
stuff and it's probably things that they
historically have with the business.
I think I understand that you guys are
starting to push in like from an actual
product standpoint and service
standpoint, you guys are starting to
touch more of like the AI industry and
and
it's related from a capability
perspective, probably not industries
that people would expect you guys to be
showing up in.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
I would say there's a big misperception
and then started there, So, I'm glad you
came back to this of what of who Koch
is.
A lot of people think of Koch as like
where we started as a, you know, a large
private industrial company.
>> I thought you were out pumping
[clears throat] oil yourself.
>> Well, I did [laughter] do a lot of that.
I had all the teenage jobs every summer
working in refineries and feed yards and
gas liquids plants. So, I cut my teeth
on that. That is true. But if you look
at
Koch today, I mentioned we touched the
majority of the economy. We're in
everything from wood products to glass
manufacturing to agriculture.
Um, but we're more of a technology
company than an industrial company. Um,
I think that's a better framing for what
reality is today. We've spent We've
invested 50 billion over the last
eightish years.
And those are um, two ex- two
>> In technology, sorry.
Um, and two examples would be that are
two of our, I would say, 12 different
business platforms that we have are just
pure technology companies. One would be
Infor. Um, that um, that's actually um,
has been based here in New York City.
But that's ERP software, right? So, when
we acquired Infor, that was that brought
us
north of 30,000 software engineers
overnight. So, you can imagine from a
capability lens what that did to teach
us technology and how we should be
applying
um
>> W- Why would Koch buy an ERP software
platform? Like again, you know,
oil, hay, cattle.
>> said it in your question, capabilities.
Um, we recognized that we were behind in
software and how our businesses were
running. And we we had some
old, you know, a lot of different
software systems that were kind of
um, holding some of the companies
together with bubble gum and bailing
wire. Just we were under-invested there.
So, I think when the Infor opportunity
came around, um we saw that that could
be a new capability for Koch. Not just a
new business, but it could teach the
rest of the companies about um
how to run a business more efficiently,
how to understand our customer better,
how to have better analytics um in our
supply chain, right? And so, that's
that's
kind of getting into our business
development approach as well. And if if
you look at if you look at the history
of Koch, that I think this could be
helpful to your audience as well.
Um and the evolution of it. One of the
biggest differentiators was our
application of the principle
capabilities.
So,
how did Koch go from being a small
southern Oklahoma crude oil gathering
company to one that touches the majority
of the economy? A lot of people are
like, "Well, how does all that make
sense?"
And it is these principles that we're
talking about, but one in particular is
capabilities. We have looked at the
growth of Koch through the lens almost
like of horizontal capabilities as
opposed to vertical industries. So, when
you think about business that way of
like, "Where where am I strongest? What
have I demonstrated to customers where I
can add unique value and build
competitive advantage?" Koch started
around um engineering,
um
uh heavy operations. So, you know,
refiners, pipe refineries, pipelines,
um
things that required significant
investment that were that were difficult
to operate. We had a strong capability
there. And then trading and logistics.
We're pretty good at moving product from
product from point A to point B and
really optimizing that for the customer.
So, when you combine those three things,
those were our core capabilities that we
looked at and said, "Okay, instead of
well, we want to get bigger in
pipelines. We want to go from whatever
20% market share to 40% market share or
the same in refining where where we
started." We looked at it and said,
"Where can we apply those three
capabilities across other industries
that are maybe slightly depressed where
we can get in at a reasonable valuation,
test and learn and bring those
capabilities horizontally into new
industries?" Whether it that was in
fertilizers and agriculture. Like we we
we got into that in rough 2003 buying
farmland out of bankruptcy.
Um Georgia-Pacific 2005 wood products.
How do How does pipelines and refineries
relate to that? Well, those three
capabilities I described, we could bring
that value to wood products. We could
bring that to agriculture. So, I would
say um that's a very different way to
look at business business development
where you want to grow because a lot of
companies and I think public companies
fall into this trap as well. It's just
how do I just get more market share in
my vertical industry whereas we look at
it horizontally.
>> I I've heard
your dad Charles and you both talk about
this where
this like capability component it almost
prevents you from thinking of we're an
oil company. We're a you know,
agriculture business. It's very much
hey, we're really good at moving things.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> That's right. What else can we move?
That's it.
>> And I think that some of the great have
done that and you know, you can even
look at something like a Berkshire. Like
what is their
competitive advantage? It's like they're
really good at allocating capital. And
it kind of doesn't matter what the
underlying business is. They're in
everything from candy to you know,
Apple. Right? But but they're really
good at understanding business and
underwriting you know, risk and downside
and then allocating capital. You guys I
think do that. But what I think people
probably don't understand is a lot of
these opportunities my understanding is
some of them are offensive where you
guys are going out. But you guys also
have become so large and so well
respected that I think you guys get a
lot of phone calls.
>> Yes.
>> And people are like, "Hey, you know,
there's this thing in bankruptcy, you
know, are you guys interested?" Or um
yes, it sounds like maybe even the ERP
software was more of like somebody
brings it to you rather than you guys
are hunting for ERP software.
>> Yeah.
>> And so having that framework of like, we
know what we stand for, we know kind of
what we want to be in, we understand
what our capabilities are, but we also
understand where we're weak, when these
opportunities come up, I'm assuming it
makes the decision-making much like more
efficient in terms of do we want to
spend time on this or not?
>> It it does. Um but we are a lot of
people would think, "Okay, we've got
some five-year plan to grow the company,
in which industries we want to be in."
We're uh much more reactive and
opportunistic.
And so Molex is a great example of this.
Um we we acquired Molex in 2013. Molex
is one of the largest connector um
companies in the world, connectors and
cables.
Um they're in everything from your
iPhone to um
uh healthcare devices. They've got a you
know, whole healthcare with Philips
Medisize. They're in um automobiles as
well with as um autos have They're
basically computers on wheels.
Um and then we're in data centers as
well, the connectors and the cabling.
So, um
when we when we got that opportunity,
and that was owned by the Krehbiel
family, and that was a public company
for
30, 40 years. But the Krehbiel family
had um
um majority control over that, but they
wanted to um they didn't have a
succession plan.
And they wanted the ability to maintain
the brand and the legacy over time, and
look at a company that that would would
continue to invest in it, and would
could be a would be a great long-term
home. So, that opportunity came about
because I think we had built that brand
over time. And the Molex story is
amazing because we we ended up acquiring
that. Um we convinced the Krehbiel
family that Koch would be a good home
for it. We acquired it. And but we
didn't know a lot of we know anything
about cabling and connectors at the
time. But we have a team that is within
the Koch equity development team that is
excellent at um analysis, you know,
looking at industries, but also being a
capital solution provider. And
understanding the you know, the family
in terms of what are their goals and
then how do we wrap a capital solution
around that? There's a lot of different
examples that that we've done there in
family-owned businesses specifically. Um
but with Molex, we looked at that and
that team said like look this the future
is IoT.
Like this room, right? It's it's going
to be connected. There's going to be
data so you can optimize it whether it's
a plant, a product, um IoT is is a wave
of the future and we don't really
understand that. That is a capability
gap for Koch.
So when you look at the mutual benefit
of the Molex deal um we could help the
Krehbiel family, but they could help us
by getting into IoT, but then applying
our principles to that to help it grow,
stay private, can you know, um get into
new areas like like data centers that
that we got into. And that's that's been
one of the most interesting stories I
think of any acquisition um that we've
done. Um I there's there's more I could
say there, but um I would say when we
bought that, one of the most important
principles uh was changing paradigms.
Because as a public company
going private and going from top-line
thinking and worrying about revenue and
revenue growth to bottom-line value
creation.
And a more and then also shifting from
there was a lot of top-down
I would say, decision-making as well,
where we've we've tried to move that
culture over time to bottom-up
empowerment. And um
it's a case study in terms of
transforming the return on capital of a
business with principles.
And so there's more I could say there,
but both on the business like how we
think about growth at Coke, that's a
great example, filling a capability gap
with technology. Um but then also having
to change a paradigm culturally within
the organization.
>> So how do you take a business let's use
this example or another business.
You acquire the business, they're giving
you the business and selling it to you
because reputation, you've got the
capital, you understand what they need,
etc. But then I'm assuming that the
operating principles and the operating,
you know, kind of day-to-day tempo is
very different, especially for a public
company versus going to private,
top-line revenue versus profit-oriented.
And you said something to me one time
which I just keep thinking about is like
the holy grail of every business owner
is what if your people knew what to do
without you having to tell them?
>> [laughter]
>> I was like, oh, this guy if he can if he
can teach people to do that, that'd be
amazing.
>> Yeah.
>> But like how how do you implement or get
to that end result with whether it's
Molex or another business that you guys
acquire? Because I think it's different.
If you're starting a company, you get a
hand pick, okay, here's the people we're
going to put into it. They already come
with our operating principles, they
already understand how we do things.
That's the DNA of the company from day
one is Coke.
>> Yeah.
>> It's different when you buy a company
and you bring it in. Now you almost have
to, you know, kind of change the plane
or build a plane while you're in midair.
And so you're trying to get all of the
people now have to go from maybe
top-down leadership to, no, you're going
to know what to do without us telling
you what to do.
>> Yeah.
>> But we're not going to change many of
the people.
>> Yeah, I mean your statement is right on.
And when people have never heard of
Coke, never heard of principle-based
management, I always say, imagine a
business where people at scale, people
know what to do without being told.
Um and then people are like, "Well,
that's that sounds wild, right?" Just
like your reaction to me on that. But,
um to be clear, that's a vision. That's
not reality.
Um but, you have to start with like what
what is the culture that you're aspiring
to have?
And so, if if if you have that as a
mindset, then you truly have you're
moving towards bottom-up empowerment as
opposed to top-down control and
dependency. Cuz let's let's take the the
other side of that, where you have the
smartest guy in the room, the the leader
that is setting all the strategies, that
is making all the big calls, and then
telling the 10 the 10 other leaders
around the table, you do this, you do
that, you need to go get this customer,
and that.
You're missing out on all of the
knowledge downstream of that leader. To
empower those other 10 leaders to say,
"You're closest to the opportunity.
You're closest to the customer. You're
closest to the problem.
Um go figure out and innovate the best
way to create the most value."
Um I'll give you an example of this.
Like,
my And so, this is my father's approach.
And as we talked about before, it kind
of the culture is downstream of the
leader. Like, you you you know, if if my
father ran Coke top-down, and he wanted
to make every decision, well, you're
going to have that throughout all the
supervisors um within Coke. But, his
approach is more my comparative
advantage is
um around these abstract concepts and
principles, and how do I teach leaders
this to carry it into the business, and
then let them run, right? So, um the
rest of the leaders see that and are
like, "Oh, wow. I have permission. He's
empowering me. Now, I have permission to
empower my people. Am I running my
business top-down? Am I telling everyone
what to do? Am I acting like the
smartest guy in the room?
And so that has is I think one of the
I'd say the the biggest differences
culturally. But to your point, doing an
acquisition
and where you bring in one that was run
more from top-down and there's a lot of
dependency on the leader to make call
the shots.
It takes years.
It takes many many years to do that. But
I mean you have to change out talent.
You got to get the right leaders in the
right roles. But I think once you have
the leaders that really have a
principle-based approach, you see the
results almost immediately.
>> Mhm.
>> And and also the results from the water
cooler talk in the company. What do the
employees really say about their Do they
Do they love what they're doing? Are
they self-actualizing? Do they feel like
they're empowered? Do they have the
flexibility to innovate? And so but but
yeah,
growth is a challenge from an
acquisition standpoint.
>> I don't know why I never thought of this
before, but
um
do you think that Charles got some of
this idea because his father, your
grandfather, said to him, "Come back and
run the company and you can do whatever
you want except for you got to get my
permission to sell it."
>> I mean
Fred Fred leading by example there.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean he said, "Come back and run Koch
Engineering." And he knew my dad didn't
have a lot of experience in it. But and
he started him on a really hard
business.
>> Mhm. For for context for those that
don't know, um Fred Koch is uh
>> My my grandfather.
>> And he had Koch Engineering.
Your father, Charles,
>> That's right.
>> probably was not that interested in
coming and running the business. And
basically your grandfather convinced him
to come back by saying, "Here's the keys
to the kingdom. It's not a huge
business, but you know, it's we got
something that started. That's it. Go
knock yourself out. Do whatever you want
except for sell the company."
>> Yeah, I mean a case in point, this was a
time where when he came in my father
came into the company, and my
grandfather asked him to do that, there
was only 300 employees at Coke. Today, I
mentioned there's 145,000, so I remember
my first job,
I was 15 years old, I was employee
8,548.
And so, to we
>> Who's counting?
>> Yeah, yeah, [laughter] right.
But, I it just it goes to we've seen so
much in terms of the both failures and
successes of the company, and I just
high-level message,
um
you know, from the book and all the
learnings and all the stories that we
tell, we learn a hell of a lot more from
failure than we do success.
>> It's interesting this idea of failure
because, um, one of the themes that I
take out of
multiple books I've read now, I think
even actually I've read some of the
book, I don't know if you know this,
I've read some of the books that I would
say the critics have written, and I
always like reading,
um, you know, there's
a book that was written about,
um, one of the Murdochs, right? There
was a book that was written about Peter
Thiel, and it's like very much like the
negative slant. And what I find
interesting about them is like, one, you
kind of get both sides of the story,
right? But, the, um, anecdotes from the
critics are always like the most absurd
kind of things, whatever.
>> Sure.
>> But, throughout every single book, one
through line, and even in some of the
public commentary, is
we almost went bankrupt. We almost went
bankrupt. And it's like, you know,
Purina, and like we can go through like
maybe there's four or five of these
examples that are constantly talked
about. And so, like, how much of the
success that the business has today was
you had to be willing to take the risk
of almost putting the business out of,
you know, almost going out of business
in order to drive, you know, 10,000 or
10,000 X growth?
>> Yeah,
well, we didn't have to make those dumb
decisions.
>> [laughter]
>> Um, but what what the way we describe it
is that we learned a lot from those
failures, and we we we learned what
principle we missed
um or probably set of principles that we
missed um to basically dig ourselves out
of the ditch and and transform and
started applying the principles. So
Purina is a great example and we tried
to basically um in the the ag world
basically be part of the entire value
chain. It was called the gas to bread
spread. Everything we were bringing
pulling natural gas out of the ground to
make the nitrogen that was then planted
to to um to grow the food and then pizza
crusts on the the the you know the the
um
at the grocery store.
And
uh what you realize is that we we had
very quickly in a short period of time
completely violated almost all of our
principles.
Um where are your true capabilities?
Where can you add value? We violated
experimental discovery. We plunged into
things and made huge bets without really
understanding them.
And um yeah, I mean like that Purina was
bankrupt the day we bought it because we
didn't do we didn't apply the scientific
method, another one of our principles,
to the diligence process and said, "What
are all the reasons we should not do
this deal?"
And so when you have that mindset and
everyone's full board, we got to get
this deal done. We got to be have this
whole gas to bread spread vision,
then what you're going to do is like
look the other way on some of the
diligence. And so we find ourselves day
one out of the you know um that we
acquired a bunch of out of the money hog
contracts that were hundreds of millions
of dollars under underwater. So I mean
just think about two principles I went
through there. Where are your true
capabilities? Focus on that. Don't try
to overgrow into all these different
value chains that that you have no
business being in. But then also um
experimental discovery.
Um it's okay to
Um, but make a responsible sized bet
that is basic you know, that is close to
or equal to the size of your knowledge.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? And we talk about failure as it's
not a failure if you're really driving
experimental discovery and the value of
the learning exceeds the the the cost of
the loss or the failure.
>> Mhm.
>> And so I think that's
being a private company, thinking very
long-term. If you're worried about, you
know, it's like we got a little red ink
in the next 3 months, you're not going
to be driving those experiments. Right?
And so we try to have a very robust
experimental discovery culture
um, to where every capability, every
individual, every business, they're
coming to the quarterly business reviews
with here's where I'm experimenting,
here's where I'm innovating and they're
not beat down because they're like,
"Hey, we we shut this experiment down
and this one and this one." It's like,
"Well, what did you learn? How are you
going to apply that to your future
strategy?"
>> Today's episode is brought to you by
Arch Public. Arch Public has just
expanded its agentic trading platform
beyond crypto. So pay attention, this is
a big one. Now, they are automating
strategies across stocks, commodities
and ETFs and I think that this is going
to be huge. You can now automatically
take profits when one market hits new
all-time highs and rotate that capital
into other markets showing more [music]
opportunity. Whether you're rotating
capital into AI stocks, gold, if you're
investing in the S&P 500 or accumulating
Bitcoin, Arch Public brings real
discipline and automation to your
investment strategy. Additionally,
they've launched a powerful new tax loss
harvesting tool. With crypto being so
volatile and its exemption from the wash
sale rule, Arch Public can offset gains
with losses without compromising your
long-term positions. It's exactly what
every serious investor does.
Institutional grade automation that
works across every major asset class.
There's no more emotional trading, no
more missing tax opportunities, just
smarter, hands-free execution of your
preferred strategies. Go to
archpublic.com
right now. Connect with their team, set
up a time, bring your account in if
you'd like, then you can learn what
automated trading can do for you.
archpublic.com
Today's episode is brought to you by
Uphold. Are you someone who's tired of
juggling multiple apps just to trade,
earn, stake, or spend your crypto? Then
listen up because Uphold does all of
that in one single unified platform. You
can access 300-plus crypto and fiat
currencies with an interface that works
for you, whether you're a beginner or an
expert. Uphold also features any-to-any
swaps where you can swap crypto to fiat,
fiat to metals, and tokens to tokens
directly in the app. If you prefer
self-custody, Uphold's vault gives you
multi-sig security, key recovery, direct
trading access, and peace of mind
without giving up convenience. Uphold is
also 100% reserved, meaning no
fractional practices, and proof of
reserves are updated every 30 seconds so
you can verify your assets anytime. For
US users, you can even earn yield on
dollars with a USD interest account. No
fees, no minimums, and funds are insured
up to $2.5 million
through the Atomic [music]
Cash Sweep Program. If you want one app
for your entire digital asset life,
check out uphold today. Go to uphold.com
[music] to learn more. uphold.com
Go check them out today. I read a book
about talked a lot about legacy, and one
of the things that it talks about is,
you know, the rise of meritocracy has a
lot of benefits.
>> Yeah.
>> But there are certain examples
throughout history where actually
meritocracy is a negative. And one of
the example he uses like take a farmer.
If you're like the fifth generation
farmer, you're not like, "Who's the
single best farmer who can go get 10%
better yield out of this farm?" You're
like, "Hey, I want this to continue to
provide for my kids and grandkids and
great-grandkids, etc." And so like you
train your kids to take this thing over.
>> Yeah.
>> When it comes to failure, do you have an
advantage because there's
this element of like you are part of the
Coke family and if somebody else was,
you know, in that disruptive technology,
like in a weird way
6 months, 9 months, 12 months, 2 years
of losses, like at some point do they
kind of get whacked, right? It's like,
"Hey, this isn't working."
But almost in a weird way, maybe there's
some genius to, you know, you and and
your father, etc., saying like, "No,
let's put the person who actually
[snorts] has the intestinal fortitude to
be able to see this very long term and
know that the losses are going to come
early in disruptive technology." Like,
is that an advantage?
>> I mean, I think the outcome of that
could be that wasn't part of the thought
process. It was just more of there's a
market opportunity. We need to be in
venture to see if the you're talking
Coke disruptive technologies and why I
started that and that line aligned with
my comparative advantage and my passion
of what I could where I could add the
most value.
>> positioned to do it from your interest.
>> yeah. Now, I'm not running that anymore
um because it had been built up and it
was growing and it was in a position
where I know my where my weaknesses are.
You know, you mentioned like
you know, I don't know if we're happy
about our failures or how but I learned
a hell of a lot from being in roles that
I shouldn't have been cuz what I
realized is I'm a builder, not an
operator. I'm not not a good operator.
>> And what is what you've said this a
couple times I've seen. Like, what what
is the difference between those in your
mind?
>> Um
I would say I'll just give you concrete
examples of different roles that I've
had. I was I spent I mentioned I spent a
decade in our fertilizer business and I
had a lot of different roles. I learned
everything from supply chain to sales,
marketing, accounting
of it and then ultimately there was an
opportunity my boss came to me and said,
"Hey, I'm going to go build an energy
business
with this fertilizer business. You take
You've been in the fertilizer business
for 7, 8 years now. You're the right one
to take this over. It's like the third
largest profit driver in Koch. So, what
an incredible opportunity.
Um but that I mean this was a
complicated business. Uh production
assets and you know, all of
we we had one of the the largest
positions in North America to
make and trade nitrogen. We had a global
business to trade nitrogen, phosphate,
potash. And so, we operated in 30
countries in this business, 4, 5,000
employees. And uh it was incredible
opportunity for me, but very quickly I
realized that operating a day-to-day
business and running a a really large
team was not my bag.
>> Mhm.
>> And um
there was someone that was much better
at it than me.
And um
and so, when you think this is the
principle of comparative advantage. And
I think being intellectually honest to
where is your real gift and also where
is it not. And what is that gift
relative to everyone else on the team?
That's that's the real important part
within comparative advantage. And um by
you being in a role, what is the
trade-off relative to what someone else
can do? But also what you could be
doing. And these are it's it sounds like
really basic. Uh I think sports teams
apply this really well. The quarterback
versus the wide receiver. It's like
obvious who should be in what role. But
for whatever reason in business, it's
more challenging to truly apply
comparative advantage. You've got egos
that get in the way. You want the big
title. I feel like I have to have
hundreds of people reporting to me and
that's my status and I've really made it
if I have that job. We think all of that
is BS. And I'm like living proof of that
because I had that job and I realized
that I'm much better at networking,
business development, origination.
Um like looking around
>> one. The zero to one is much more your
>> And and so, that's what I mean. by not a
good operator, much better builder.
>> And so it took me, you know, until I was
late 30s to realize that, early 40s.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, and but you realize through failure
at different roles that to find that out
and then and then be in the right role,
go figure out what the right role is for
you. You can you can create a lot of
value. And oh, by the way, the
fertilizer business is going to be run
by someone that is a great operator.
>> Mhm.
>> So
>> [clears throat]
>> I I find this uh is pretty common, I
think, especially in people who are
interested in technology. It it's such a
disruptive, fast-paced, like dynamic
environment that
um
they're constantly looking at what is
the new technology now, what is coming,
how can I be disrupted? Like like
they're just a a personality and a
mindset and is very different than the
person who's like
um maybe a Warren Buffett who's like,
"I'm betting on things that don't
change."
>> Yeah.
>> Right? Like that's a very different
approach than the people who are looking
for like, "What is the thing that is
going to make a massive change?" And
just naturally, if you were drawn to
disruptive technologies
then you know, it's kind of hard to have
two sides of your brain that also is
like, "I I also enjoy the things that
will not change for 20 years."
>> That's right. I mean, one of our
principles is it's Maslow's principle of
self-actualization.
And I think it's so important. You can't
um you you have to talk about
self-actualization through the lens of
comparative advantage. Like in my story
in realizing what I wasn't good at
relative to others and what I was good
at relative to others. And that that's
how Coke Disruptive Technologies was
formed, basically out of the failure of
me being president of Coke Fertilizer.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, so like
>> at it as a failure?
>> Um
>> [clears throat]
>> no, because of the value, the learning
of like what I'm not good at relative to
um because the business was still doing
fine. We just looked at it across
>> it's weird you use the word failure,
right? It's like the business was still
>> But failure relative to potential.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? Relative to what you could be
doing. And so I think this is maybe an
interesting takeaway for your audience.
If you really understand and apply the
principle of comparative advantage
on your team and you said, "Everyone is
in the right role optimized around their
gift relative to what everyone else on
the team is doing instead of looking at
your role in a vacuum."
Think if Think if you do what it's a
team of 10, team of 100, team of
100,000.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? If you had everyone in the right
role, put all egos aside. Think of the
value and the competitive advantage that
you'd have. You would have You would
field the best team
um and kick everyone's ass.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? And And I think it's overlooked.
And then to me that is the one of the
most Even at Coke, right? If there's one
that we could change the trajectory of
our application
and um like my my father always says,
"Well, I'd score Coke on principle
application at about four out of 10."
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> Wait, why?
>> Because he always looks at it and says
um once he sees the principles being
applied the it's a the horizon keeps
moving further. So the potential
[snorts]
is greater. So you're always a fourth.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> It's always a fourth.
>> going to get worried like the Godfather
of principle-based management.
>> It's a little bit tongue-in-cheek, but
there's a lot of truth to that, too,
because the more you apply the
principles, the more potential you see.
>> It's funny talking to you because out of
the entire book comparative advantage is
probably the thing that I, you know,
grabbed hold of the most and was like,
"This one principle can be applied
everywhere." And
I think that
as an individual, as a company, it's
very obvious, but even in society,
right? If you think about over the last,
I don't know, 100 years, the United
States was really good at certain things
and then we kind of like gave some of
those away and now we're trying to bring
them back and we're thinking a lot about
like, well, do we have a talent
advantage? Do we have a capital
advantage? Do we have certain
manufacturing capabilities that others
don't or you know,
geography-wise we have a huge advantage
of just two oceans and friendly
neighbors, whatever.
But I do think that that's probably one
of the aspects that is most
misunderstood about
kind of the Coke enterprise, right? Is
the same thing and you guys highlight
this now. It's like you can transform
yourself, you can transform a business
or you can transform society.
>> That's right.
>> These 41 principles plus, you know, many
others that probably didn't make it in
the book,
they can be applied at any scale and
whether it's a two-person company or
100,000 person company is the same as
you as an individual versus society.
>> That's right.
>> To me, that's actually the value of the
principles.
>> I I I we definitely agree with that
statement and kind of your takeaway from
it and um, you know, as I as we began
this interview, I I talked about that we
live in unprecedented uncertainty as a
society.
And um,
if you look at the next generation, like
Gen Z in particular,
um,
I think there's a crisis of purpose.
Um, and that
there's there's so much focus in what
other people like and where we fall into
this collective illusion
of, well, if I'm going to be accepted in
society, I have to like whatever
everyone else thinks.
Well, the the mitigant to that kind of
behavior and that thinking is having a
very clear uh, framework of principles,
right? So, you don't, back to what we're
saying before, like blow with the wind.
And so, but but going specifically to
the principles in the society that I
think we want, which is where the the
country was founded and and right there
in the Declaration of Independence, is
is principles like mutual benefit.
Right? Um
we want a society of mutual benefit
where people win because they're helping
others.
>> Mhm.
>> And if you think if if we're working
together and I help you win and you want
to help me win, well, the pie grows.
>> Mhm.
>> This isn't a zero-sum game that sadly so
many people look at society through that
lens.
We need to go from
um we need to go from zero-sum thinking
to mutual benefit. If I help other
others win, I'm going to win, too. We
need to go from
um tribalism
and divisiveness to openness and
empathy, putting yourself in someone
else's shoes. We need to um go from We
talked about bottom-up versus top-down.
We have way too much top-down control
and dependency.
>> Mhm.
>> Um I saw a stat um recently, a very
disturbing stat, that 52% of Americans
think that we can't solve our own
problems anymore.
And that so the the government needs to
come in and fix it.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? Whereas if you think of bottom-up
and we believe in people that they are
the solution because they're closest to
the problems,
then we can have a society of mutual
benefit. We can remove barriers from the
top-down and we can really advance the
American dream and why so many people
from all over the world want it have
wanted to come to America to experience
that. Go build a business, build a
family, go build the next SpaceX that no
one thought was possible. Um right? So,
that's at a high level, at least how we
see
these principles that we're looking at
and we apply that has grown Coke over
10,000 X.
We can do you can do that across
society, too, and drive the most human
progress.
>> As you're talking, um I don't think that
you would uh consider yourself and hold
yourself out as a Bitcoiner. Right? I
don't think I don't think that
I don't think that Charles Koch's got,
you know, a bag of Bitcoins somewhere,
right? [laughter]
But, what I do find very interesting is
the like Bitcoiner mentality. And
there's, you know, millions of these
people. They're very, I think,
individual sovereignty. They're very
much, you know, I want to take control
of my own life. I want to improve my
situation for my family and and my kids,
etc. I think that they have a strong
belief in uh this kind of bottoms-up
type approach of accountability,
personal responsibility, etc.
But, also I think that there is
um maybe like forget even what the
principles are, just a belief that like
you have to know yourself and you have
to stand for what you believe in.
>> Yeah.
>> Even if it's different than what other
people believe in or your neighbor or
whatever, just like knowing what your
principles are is really, really
important and then having the courage
and intestinal fortitude to stick to
them.
Forget, you know, whether it's Bitcoin,
whether it's uh principles-based
management, whatever. It's like the
people I think I have respect the most
in, you know, that I've interacted with,
they have a set of principles that they
have done the work to discover. And then
they just say, "Look,
we don't have to agree. This is what I
believe.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think there's a lot of other
people who agree with me and I want to
go, you know, build my thing with people
who see the world the same way I do."
>> That's it.
>> And that seems to be like the Koch way
of doing
>> I I think I think you're right. And I
gives you a framework to say yes and say
no to things uh based on your your value
system and based based on your
principles. And, you know, you're you're
asking about how we view this societally
um and what we do we, you know, we've
talked a lot about the business side,
but um I'd say I spend about a third of
my time and my father spends half of his
time on an organization called Stand
Together, which is all of our uh
philanthropy and social change, which is
basically
the whole idea of bottom-up empowerment
and believing in people and believing
those that are closest to the problem
are the ones that are the solution to
the problem. And we have we have
hundreds of examples cuz we work on
Stand Together is this organization that
has been
built up over we started in 2003, but my
dad's been working on social change for
most of his life 60 plus years. But he
realized that if we're going to make a
a really big impact and create movements
that help people around some of these
biggest problems, some of the biggest
problems in the country,
that you had needed a network effect on
that that we needed partnerships. We
needed preferred partnerships that all
believe in this these principles and
this idea that every human being has a
gift, but there's all these there's new
barriers stacked up against people every
day that make it impossible for them to
unlock the potential of their gift. And
that's what Stand Together is about. So
we work on poverty, addiction, violent
you know, violence,
criminal justice reform, transforming
education, very very broad set problem
set. But we have over a thousand
business leaders now that invest their
philanthropic dollars, invest their time
to get behind a problem that they care
about most. And now we're we're we're
leveraging culture to do that at
movement scale now with
sports, music, media, YouTube, and
getting you know, and getting these
these principles out that we've talked
about and trying to help people at
scale.
>> What's an example of like something
specific at Stand Together that you guys
do where the principles are kind of used
to affect change?
>> Yeah. I would say
I'll start on education.
I think that's something that every
household in America cares about.
>> Nobody wants their kid to be dumb.
>> No one wants their kid to be dumb. I
think everyone's generally concerned
with the
especially the K through 12 education
system.
We believe it's broken. But there's some
really positive bright spots. And so our
vision for education and applying these
principles into the institution of
education is one of going from a
one-size-fits-all
teach-to-test teacher at the front of
the classroom model
to you know working from textbooks to
individualized education. And now that
we have new models and technology that
that gives students the ability to do
that at scale, we have a huge
opportunity in front of us.
I always use the example of what Sal
Khan created with Khan Academy with
leveraging technology to
meet a kid where they are in their
learning journey and all kids in you
know 30
30 kid classroom, they're all at
different levels, right? But for them to
master a class mathematics or
physics or whatever the
subject is, they can do it on their own
on their own terms. And they're not
trying to graduate everyone from grade
to grade. The Alpha school is another
great example where they're leveraging
AI for the first two hours of an
8-hour day
basically cramming the curriculum into
two hours and then giving them the
freedom to choose based on what they're
passionate about different projects they
want to work on.
Do they want to stand up a podcast
because they're passionate about that
learn public speaking? All these things
that are so critical to when you get out
in the real world, that's what you have
to know.
Financial literacy, almost no school
teaches that.
>> And these new models, these micro
schools, the Alpha schools that I'm
describing, are teaching that to kids in
kindergarten and like first through
third grade. What an advantage. These
practical things. So, um, the thing
that's most exciting about education to
me is that, um, prior to COVID, only 20%
of families were open to a new model for
their kids. Post-COVID, after families
have seen, um, you know, when their
their kids came home and they saw that
their learning more on YouTube than they
were at school, that, um, 80% are now
open to a different model. And that's
why we we've invest we have something
called the VELA Fund, which is basically
venture capital for education
entrepreneurs that we we pulled together
with the Walton family that, um, we've
put uh, we created a fund and others
stand together, um, uh, partners have
invested in this. But we've built over
5,000 micro schools across the country
in the last five or six years. And it's
all around these principles of
individualized education, helping kids
find their gift, and putting them on
that self-actualization journey earlier
in life. We feel like that's I mean,
that's the future. Every All these other
problems, addiction,
um, mental health issues, um, our our
broken criminal justice system are
downstream of a bad education.
Right? So, if you if we can really
transform the education system in this
country, we'll be we'll be way better
off.
>> I was talking with a friend recently,
um, and uh, he has uh, kids about the
same age as mine, and he told me that he
created, uh, what he calls a, uh, chore
chart. And so, you know, three four
three So, what he does is basically he
lists out a couple chores, and every
night before the kid goes to bed, they
check to see, "Did did the chores?" And,
um, he is, uh, I I forget I think he's
paying a dollar a day or something,
right? But the idea is just like, hey,
you have chores you have to do. And so,
I think great idea, so I created it for
two of my kids, and they're so excited
to do chores. I'm sure that will wear
off over time, right? But what I started
realizing is like,
I'm responsible for them
knowing this stuff. Not somebody else,
right? And so, I go and I look and I'm
like, okay.
I don't know whatever the latest
percentage is of kids who, you know,
can't read past a third grade level or,
you know, whatever. I mean, there's this
balance. I I fully understand there are
parents who are working two jobs, and
they don't have time, and you know, all
this kind of stuff.
>> Right.
>> But there's a heck of a lot of parents
who are just kind of outsourcing their,
you know, education of their kids to
somebody else and saying, well, like,
why aren't you doing a good job, right?
And I'm always reminded of Clayton
Christensen, The Innovator's Dilemma. He
wrote another book called uh How Will
You Measure Your Life? It's one of my
favorite books. And in it, one of the
like warnings that he gives is, do not
outsource the raising of your children
to other people. And he talks about the
soccer coach. You don't know what their
values are. You don't know what they're
telling your kids if you're not at
practice and all. Doesn't mean don't
have your kid play soccer. Just means
that like, you also are responsible for
telling your kid, you know, how to
perform on the field or what the rules
are or whatever.
>> Right.
>> It sounds like you guys are in these
kind of micro schools really empowering
the parents along with a teacher to say,
hey look, let's shrink down these class
sizes and be able to spend more time on
the things that actually matter, not
just the rote memorization of the books.
>> That's right. And I think one um one
critical distinction is we don't think
about a teacher as a teacher, think
about them as a guide.
So, the the kid the the student has
agency.
The student gets to decide, and whether
it's Alpha or the micro school that my
kids go to in Wichita, Kansas,
they decide what most of their day looks
like. And I think that that is a
paradigm shift, right? You you know,
like
>> us doing that?
>> Yeah, no, exactly. I mean, I grew up in
system where it was teach the test. I
went to a great school, but
um I look at what what my kids and so
many more kids have access to at a low
cost, by the way.
Um
>> And my guess is like on this point,
right?
If we went back in time and somebody
showed up for one day in like high
school and was like, "What do you guys
want to do today?"
I don't know, you know, we didn't know
each other then, but I'm sure that we'd
kind of be like, "I don't know, like eat
candy, not do anything, you know,
definitely not be here at school."
But if that is just the normal
day-to-day,
>> Yeah.
>> you don't go to the extreme of like, you
know, screwing around and, you know,
doing the worst thing possible. It's
kind of like, well, I think kids do want
to learn. I think they do want to do
things that are cool.
>> What what what we're doing is closing
the motivation gap.
>> Mhm.
>> Joe Lehmann says that 90% of why you
have a failing student is because he's
not motivated to learn.
>> Mhm.
>> And [clears throat] so what he's doing
with these techniques and making it fun
and interesting and meeting the kid
where they are,
um is
is closing the motivation gap. I was
like, "Oh, actually, well, do I have
flexibility in the way I learn?
Um I can do this with gaming and like
somehow like Fortnite comes into this.
That's my favorite game and I'm going to
learn. There's an incentive there of if
I really focus on eating my vegetables,
right? And uh and learning my math and
learning uh learning the science and all
all the the the things that I get to
learn also in the afternoon through
Fortnite and then I can I can work on
projects that I'm excited about."
I'll give you an example of my my own
son, my oldest um son, because of that
flexibility,
um you one of his uh best friends, 13
years old, uh when when um
Anthropic released Claude code, um one
of the kids got really good at it and he
came up the curve quickly and then my
son Charlie was like, "Hey, I want to
let's do a project together."
And then within like a month, he comes
home and he's showing me what he's
working on and he's like, "Pop, why do
you have that spreadsheet there?" Like I
don't know, I had something my my
workout program or my stretching
program. He's like, "Let me just build
you a model." So, he took that and he's
13 years old, ingested that and had an
app built on my phone in about 35
minutes.
I watched him do it. And
and then so
think if we can have all kids that have
this amazing curiosity and they all have
gifts, these tools and just let them run
and let them learn and do it on projects
that they care about, you you close the
motivation gap.
And that that alone will transform our
entire education system.
>> Wow, your kid does that for you.
>> Yeah.
>> Then builds confidence they can solve
problems, then thinks critically, then
goes and develops a comparative
advantage, right? And then just feeds
from there.
>> Yeah.
>> Before I let you go,
investing. We spent very little time on
that.
You all drive a ton of profit. You can
reinvest it into businesses. You can go
buy new businesses. There's also a whole
universe of investment assets out there
you can buy. How do you guys just
philosophically think about allocating
the money?
>> Yeah, so
I would go back to one of our
principles, long-term thinking versus
short-term thinking. So, we apply that
to to all of our investments. Um
we do invest in pretty much every asset
class there is and I think when you look
at Coke big picture, um about half of it
is those is eight operating businesses
and then we have four investment
businesses that as I mentioned covered
every asset class from early stage
venture capital all the way to investing
in in funds and investing in credit
strategies and whatnot. Um
>> So, eight operating businesses and then
four like investments.
>> Four investments. But but um, half of
our capital consumed is in the business,
but half of Coke is in these investment
businesses, right?
>> That's interesting.
>> Yeah, so um, and I think that's another
thing that people don't don't know about
Coke, but we want to we want to create
we want to have enough optionality and
liquidity to where when the next Georgia
Pacific, the next Molex comes around, we
have the dry powder so that we we can
act and we can act quickly. And I think
being private um, with an incredible
um, board that um, we can get together
within 24 hours on an opportunity that
creates a big competitive advantage for
us in the in the business development
world.
Um, what [clears throat] I would say one
area that I'm specifically focused on
that I think is
one of the biggest opportunities for
Coke long-term is on this trend of
generational wealth transfer in
businesses, especially family
businesses. If you look at the turnover
of wealth over the next 20 years is
north of a hundred trillion.
Uh, so they just stagger staggering
numbers and that creates business
opportunity.
And so family-owned business in
particular, private family-owned
businesses that are mature, we're
looking at um, you know, uh, businesses
that have significant cash flow and
meaningful EBITDA. We we have proven
over time that we think long-term about
those and that we can be a great home
for those companies, whether it's a
minority investment or uh, a
a full, you know, acquisition.
We approach the market and especially
these these family-owned businesses and
the principals of these companies with a
capital solution provider uh, mindset.
And um, we want to our goal is to be the
first call with these family businesses
when they run into problems such as
succession.
Um, they need private equity out cuz
private equity is is not thinking
long-term and they need to close a fund
and they they want off the cap stack or
growth capital.
And so
that's a a big part of what I do um
because I can I have the ability to tell
the Koch story. I think
multi-generational company. We've been
through all the family problems, so we
get it. We get it, right? And so to be
able to go into the market and say Koch
could be a great home just like it's
been for Infor, for Molex.
Um, one of the more recent um uh deals
we've done is with the DeSoto family
with uh Miter.
Um, um
a lot there was an opportunity to um to
buy into that company and then
uh supply growth capital to them and but
also bring these principles to um into
MI Windows and Doors.
We were able to prove ourselves by
making a relatively small investment
um in the company um
that ultimately grew from roughly a $300
million investment in that company to
$1.5 billion over time
um because we are a preferred partner to
them.
And we helped them grow from, you know,
60 million EBITDA or sorry 80 million
EBITDA to roughly 600 million EBITDA
over the course of, you know, five or
six years through growth growth capital.
And so that that's an example of being a
capital solution provider, understanding
the family's problems and opportunities
and then um thinking long-term. And so
business development, back to your
question, that's that's where we want to
be and we hope that we earn that brand
over time
and continue to hopefully be top of mind
in that first call for the next big
opportunity.
>> Well, if uh
as I've talked with you more and more, I
think that one thing that is very clear
is uh I always say that you can't fake
good kids, right? And
those Sunday lessons you may have been
listening more than you thought.
>> Oh, [laughter] well, I yeah, at some
point my father says
my father says I can't remember the
quote, but
sometimes
these ideas penetrate even the dullest
of minds.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> You know what I'm laughing about? My
brother was laughing the other day. We
used to tell our parents that we didn't
need to study cuz we would just put the
textbook underneath our bed and osmosis
would work, right?
We just said enough in our brain so
we'll do well on the test. And you know,
your parents are like you're
>> It's true, but it's true. It's through
personal experience and failure.
>> Yeah.
>> That's how that's how you learn.
And one thing before we we close here
that I would like to say to your
audience is
it seems like these principles can be
like so daunting, right? Like in the
book we said there's 41 principles.
There's no magic number to 41. Those are
just the ones that we have found that
have really helped us transform
and that we we feel like apply most to
society and apply to every aspect of
life, but the power of technology to
apply principles now
I'd encourage your audience to download
and check out an app that that that we
built called the Principle Companion
that really we launched with the book,
but
it's instead of looking at it as I got
to read this book and I got to you know,
learn all 41 principles and try to
figure out how to apply this. That
starts with whatever problem that you
have right now today and you engage with
it just like chat GPT one field,
whatever your problem is, type it in and
engages with you in a way that teaches
you principles to solve problems.
>> Interesting.
>> So a 5-minute exercise. So you can learn
one or two principles, get a win, get
some momentum and then learn more. It
becomes like well, that helped me with
my day. It helped me with my boss. It
helped me with my employees. It helped
me think about strategy differently in
in my business. It helped me
on how I interact with the kids at the
dinner table.
And so I'd encourage them to check that
out and just take the problem you're
dealing with right now and see if that
gives you momentum in learning one or
two principles and then and then uh I
think you'll learn more over time.
>> How can people get the app?
>> So uh they can download it in any of the
app stores. So Apple app stores or
Google Play. Um it's it's in it's in all
the technology uh platforms.
>> Amazing.
>> Yeah.
>> The book is called Becoming a
Principle-Driven Leader, 41 Principles
to Build an Enduring Business.
Um
I think the part that I enjoyed the most
was uh
I cuz I've read Charles's books, I kind
of think I understand how he writes a
little bit and his thought process. You
and him together, you guys got to write
another
>> thank you.
>> You guys got to write another one now.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, it was so fun. You know, my mom
said to my father after his first book,
he said, "You'll you'll write your next
book with your next wife."
>> [laughter]
>> And he wrote five and she's still with
him. So
um but he has he has you know, I mean it
is a process.
>> Yeah.
>> But I learned more in the last 18 months
than I've learned in the last 18 years.
>> But it's probably you have to write it
down.
>> You got it you got it you
>> Like by writing it down it makes it more
concrete.
>> it and writing it and I would encourage
like look
every business leader to have a clear
set of values and principles and capture
the stories of your failures. And get
those out so those stories aren't lost.
That's what we're trying to do with this
book [clears throat] and why my dad's on
his fifth book. This is my first one,
but um is that yeah, I mean we want to
we want Coke to learn from these stories
so we don't make the same mistakes, but
really empower people these with these
principles, but we offer it outside of
Coke because everyone's like well, why
would you take that competitive
advantage and offer it to anyone else
cuz
we want to see as many people transform
their lives as possible with these
principles. We've seen it across social
change, we've seen it across nonprofits,
we've seen it in our own lives, and
we've seen it in our own business. We
just want as many people out there to
have that the opportunity to transform
their lives, too.
>> Well, I think it's amazing. I highly
recommend everyone go get the book, and
we'll do this again in the future.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Anthony. Appreciate it.